...
Previously on Fringe:
No, no, no. No, it can't be.
Not again.
If we can send the boy
into the future, they'll realize all that he is...
-...and never go down that path.
- Observers will never exist.
They will never invade.
- Michael is how we're gonna see Etta again.
- We've still got a long way to go.
These things we've collected,
how can they be used to defeat the Observers?
They are part of a device
that we must build.
There's something I need you to do.
This is the trigger I need.
It's an initiating reactor.
It's lost its charge.
Without this piece, I cannot reset time.
If your plan is successful,
we will cease to exist.
If our plan doesn't succeed,
they will cease to exist.
After all this time,
the feelings you had for these people...
...the feelings we all had...
...they have not grown in you?
When we first came...
...when we started to experience
emotive development by being in this era...
...we agreed, the 12 of us,
to speak nothing of it.
You lost control, as did August.
When we first came here, we did not know
the true nature of our expedition.
We were not told.
The people of this era...
...this is their destiny.
Destiny can be changed...
...but you have to have
the will to change it...
...even if it requires sacrifice.
I took a risk even coming to see you...
...because I believe that the people
of this era are worth saving.
It needs to be at a 22 degree angle.
Twenty-two degrees. Can you hear me?
Blasted thing. What I wouldn't give for an
old-fashioned tumor-inducing cell phone.
I can hear you. Twenty-two degrees.
Copy that.
And make sure it's on an even plane.
Absolutely crucial.
Okay. Stop.
- We're there.
- What's the energy meter reading?
Do you see a red light on?
- Hello.
- It's me. Where are you?
We have the boy. We're on our way.
Once news starts breaking,
I wanna be out.
I'm gonna get a few things we need
and come to you.
Good enough. We'll speak soon.
Where are you right now?
We have the boy. We're on our way.
Once news starts breaking,
I wanna be out.
I'm gonna get a few things we'll need
and come directly to you.
- Here you are, sir. The checkpoints.
- Thank you, Carol. I, um...
I'll be gone for the rest of the afternoon.
Agent Broyles. I would like a word with you.
You are aware we had a level one
security breach today...
...resulting in the abduction of a high-value
detainee from our facility.
No. No, I didn't know that.
The fugitives knew precisely where
we were holding the prisoner.
You think that information came
from someone in my division?
We are exploring all possibilities.
I have heard...
...whispers...
...that the resistance operative
known as The Dove may be among us.
If that were true, whoever it is
should have been read and exposed long ago.
I do not wish to keep you
any longer from your duties.
Remain vigilant, Phillip.
Where have you been?
Why would he step off the monorail?
Why would he do that?
He knows too much. He must have known
that they wanted to harm him.
Apparently there was a reason.
There always is.
I've spoken to Anil and his men.
The magnet has been positioned
on the truck as requested.
We're missing an important part.
The initiating reactor's core decayed
substantially over the past 20 years.
I enlisted help to secure another one.
- From my time.
- An Observer?
One I trust.
But one of you will need to retrieve it.
So, what is the initiating reactor?
It provides a surge of energy
to start up the device.
The purpose of this machine
is to generate a singularity.
Essentially a small Wormhole.
Once it's open,
then we'll be able to deploy the cylinders.
They serve to stabilize each end.
One will remain here, in our present,
as an anchor.
The other one will be sent to
2167.
How do we get them to 2167?
- That's what the magnet is for.
- It's used as a launch platform.
It will hold the cylinder at the precise axis
it needs to be to enter the wormhole...
...ensuring that the cylinder
reaches its destination.
And the scrolls are to help us
set those cylinders precisely.
We'll need two generators
to power the magnet.
Already with Anil.
To run the magnet off two generators,
they have to be in perfect phase.
- We'll need a synchroscope.
- I would have thought of that.
There would be one of them in there,
probably near the fish tank.
And Michael?
He will traverse the Wormhole to 2167.
He'll meet the scientist in Oslo, Norway.
And that meeting will change
the course of human evolution.
How will he know who the scientist is?
There will be someone there to guide him.
It's Broyles.
You good?
I'm leaving for Boston.
Coming to you.
Have him on the Spring Street exit.
Number 49 northbound, lane two.
Copy, traffic control.
Bravo unit is on standby
to continue surveillance.
Bravo unit has visual.
He's 200 meters ahead, right lane.
Copy that.
- Call us when you're close.
Peter will meet you
at the entrance of the steam tunnel.
Broyles, are you there?
Can you hear me?
Hello ?
They're following me.
Windmark is letting me lead them to you.
I'll lead them around as long as I can.
But it's only a matter of time before
they realize I'm not leading them to you.
If I'm caught, they'll read me.
I can protect my thoughts,
but there's only so long that will last.
Windmark is not going to read you.
We're going to come and get you.
The most important thing is the plan.
Listen to me, Phillip,
tell me where you are.
Olivia...
-...just get it done.
- Just tell me where--
You heard him. If he is captured, it's only a
matter of time before they know we're here.
Peter. Start excavating that synchroscope.
We need to go get the new initiator.
And we need to gather everything that is
required and leave. It's our only chance.
Peter, how you going
with the synchroscope?
No synchroscope yet,
but I found some sort of syringe.
Any idea what that was for
or why you had it?
I have no idea.
This tape is addressed to me.
It's your handwriting.
Peter, I sent you a letter.
It contains something of mine.
What letter, Walter?
I imagine you called me to ask, "Why would
you send such a strange letter?"
And when you tried to call, I didn't answer...
...so you came to find me at the lab.
But I was not to be found.
I was here one moment, then vanished
from the face of the Earth the next.
I want you to know, I'm fine.
Living many, many years from now.
What is this, Walter?
You will never see me again.
You will never see me again...
...because it had to be this way
to ensure the future of our humanity.
Your future.
The future of Olivia and the future of Etta.
I don't want you to be sad.
The time we had together, we stole.
I cheated fate to be with you.
And we shouldn't have had
that time together, but we did.
And I wouldn't change it for the world
I don't want to say goodbye...
...but I will say...
...I love you, son.
I wasn't truthful with you.
I do know what that is.
It's an inoculation for time travel.
I'm taking the child Observer
into the future, Peter.
I was already inoculated in 2015.
I left this one in case
something happened to me...
...and someone else had to bring the boy
across to complete the plan.
- Does it have to be this way?
- Yes.
Why?
Because, Peter, the boy and I,
we will become a paradox.
Nature abhors a paradox.
It has to heal itself.
It does so by deleting me and the boy
at the moment of the invasion.
The boy and I will disappear after 2015.
So in order to maintain a future
without the Observers...
...you and Michael have to live out
the rest of your lives in the future.
I know in my soul
this is what I am supposed to do.
I want you to give Olivia
your daughter back.
I want to give you your life back.
As a father, how could I not do that for you?
What I said in the tape
about stealing time with you, I meant it.
I wouldn't trade it for the world.
You are my favorite thing, Peter.
My very favorite thing.
- Left it in the car?
- No, I didn't.
Hang on a second.
What happened to the part?
This was taken from one of
the original 12 scientific expedition team.
Your order to monitor
the remaining members was wise.
When December traveled to the future
and procured this unit, I was notified.
What is this?
September is assembling a device
with the fugitives.
It is a trigger containing an atomic charge...
...that is going to allow them
to create a Wormhole.
They intend to reset time.
He's in the number 6 stairwell. B Unit, cover
61st Street exit, subject's moving on foot.
Repeat, he's in the number 6 stairwell.
He knows that we know.
We can't complete the plan
because we're missing one single piece?
Without the initiating reactor,
there's no way we can open a Wormhole.
- There's not enough energy.
- The rocks provide the energy.
- To sustain the reaction, not to trigger it.
- Like a car with a full tank and no spark plug.
We're stuck.
There must be someplace we can find
another ignition source.
- Maybe we can make one.
- It's impossible.
Nothing strong enough
available in this time period.
Michael, I need your help.
When I crossed over to rescue you,
you looked at me like you expected me.
You smiled.
Like you knew I'd come for you.
Can you tell me what I should do next?
What about a shipping lane?
Of course. If we could gain
control of a shipping lane...
...we could use that as our Wormhole!
And everything else
would work as planned.
You are a genius!
This is the shipping manifest I decoded.
It's a schedule. It'll give us the location
and time of the next shipment.
- So when is it opening?
- Tomorrow morning at 6:08 a.m.
40.7787 north.
73.9776 west.
- That's New York.
- See what you can find about checkpoints.
First we need an end dock stabilizer.
What is an end dock stabilizer?
It looks like a cube.
You activate it at the location
the wormhole opens.
I know what you mean.
If we re-calibrate it,
we can reverse the polarity.
Change directional flow of the shipping lane
so that it'll send rather than receive.
- Anil?
- Broyles. He's been captured.
I put out feelers. I'll keep you informed.
What does this mean for the plan?
It's happening tomorrow morning.
There's one other thing we need first.
Peter. Hold onto these tight.
Anti-gravity osmium bullets.
Shoot Observers with these
and watch them float away like balloons.
We shoot them, they're dead.
Why do we want them to float away?
Because it's cool.
That makes sense, Walter.
Okay. Let's start loading the car.
You gonna be okay?
Walter, there's something
I want to show you.
Peter...
...I want to talk to you.
Gene.
I was gonna let her out, but I was afraid
that they would hear her moo.
Yes, she does moo quite loudly.
Especially after a meal.
I at least wanted you to see her.
You always know how to soothe me.
You always have.
Walter, this is not the end.
We're gonna win this.
And when we do, we'll be...
...drinking strawberry milkshakes
in the lab...
...and we're not even gonna remember
that this happened.
That sounds lovely.
It's a beautiful name.
What is?
Astrid.
Before we arrived here...
...we sent a team of 12.
Their mission was to observe and report
However...
...a strange phenomenon occurred.
To some degree or other...
...they succumbed to irrational emotion.
Your kind infected them.
But not you.
You seem to be impervious to everything.
I will never speak of it again...
...but I will admit this to you, Philip.
I, too, feel something.
I believe you call it...
...hate.
The feeling is mutual.
- I didn't know about it...
- Why didn't you tell us not to...?
I can handle...
What?
Remember when I told you we had
a long way to go before seeing her again?
It's not that long anymore.
We're going to see her.
We're gonna have her back.
Nothing else matters.
He's here.
Hey.
- Hi.
This is an air intake supply line.
- It leads to half the building.
- That's enough, believe me.
Good luck.
We need to get going.
We have to meet them.
I gave myself the last inoculation.
I'm going with him, Walter.
I'm taking him into the future.
I've already told Peter about my decision.
I know you once believed
this was your destiny...
...a price you had to pay.
I need this.
I have prepared myself for this.
I've been thinking about this
since I first saw the boy again.
Walter, 20 years ago, when I agreed
to let you be the one to take him...
...I didn't have the feelings I have now.
Later, when I began to realize
the height of his intellect...
...and what you call
the depths of his emotions...
...still...
...I couldn't understand what it was
that I meant to him.
And I was unable to reciprocate.
When I saw you...
...when I saw Peter...
...and saw what he meant to you...
...then I understood what my feelings were...
...and why they were important.
I can't communicate with him
in the traditional ways...
...but when I take his hand...
...and I lead him...
...he'll know that I love him.
That's being a father.
It's not about fate, Walter, yours or mine.
It's about changing fate.
It is about hope.
And protecting our children.
Think about them, Phillip.
Think about where they are.
They will understand you had no choice.
It is acceptable.
I am your ally.
Harvard University.
--In the lab...
--in the lab...
Clear the building.
Let's go, let's go.
It is entering this wing. Evacuate.
Oh, my God! No!
- I found one.
- Good, because I found something too.
We'll get you out of here.
You don't know how lucky you are
this room has no ventilation.
Trust me.
They'll set up the corridor soon.
We don't have much time.
Where are Peter and Olivia?
Olivia, where are you?
They've got the cube.
And Agent Broyles.
- I know. We're in position.
- We have to hurry.
Team 2. Engage.
- Move, move, move!
- Regroup!
Michael. Stay down.
Peter! Peter, look!
What did I say? That is cool! Ha-ha-ha!
Now, Walter!
Get the boy!
Let's go.
I love you, Dad.
I think that I would be happy
to stay here...
...for the rest of my life.
We should probably get her home, soon.
Get her into a bath,
which is never easy.
I nominate you for that one. Etta!
It's time to go.
Come on, kiddo.
It's time to go home.
You're being silly.